(It's best to view this readme in full-screen, with Word Wrap off)

Socket the Hedgeduck v0.3/SHC16 Demo
By GenesisDoes
https://eaglesoftltd.com/retro/genesis/sockth/
http://sonicresearch.org/community/index.php?threads/socket-the-hedgeduck-v0-3-demo-shc16-progress.4342/
===============================

Table of Contents:

1. About
2. Installation
3. Features
4. Credits
5. Known Bugs
6. Changelog
===============================

1. About

(No, "Socket the Hedgeduck" is not an avian O.C.; it's an in-progress modification of Sonic the Hedgehog,
which aims to port Socket/Time Dominator's levels to the Sonic the Hedgehog engine!

Boring backstory:

    During 2014, I discovered about and played a somewhat obscure Genesis game on my Genesis called
"Socket"/"Time Dominator", which many people label as a poor Sonic clone, due to it having monitor-like
powerup objects, a "High Speed Zone", spring-like objects, (poor) slope physics, checkpoints, and ring-like
collectibles for health (sparks). Although I really liked the concept of Socket and the different,
non "press-right-to-win" level layout styles and themes, I was greatly disappointed in the poor slope physics
and slow overall speed of the Socket character, and wondered if the Sonic the Hedgehog engine
would handle the levels much better.

This advanced hack is an unofficial port of Socket/Time Dominator assets
(music, level layouts, art, objects, and more) to the Sonic the Hedgehog Engine.
===============================

2. Installation

If you downloaded this hack via the version on the Sega Mega Drive & Genesis Collection
emulator on the Steam Workshop, then congratuatlions, you are ready to go play! Otherwise,
if you downloaded the ROM binary (and own a copy of the original Sonic 1), just run it on
your favorite emulator or on real hardware with a flashcart.


Otherwise, if you downloaded the IPS patch:

Find a Sonic 1 (Rev 0) ROM (don't ask me how/where!),
apply the patch(es) to ROM via an IPS patcher, play in favorite emulator
or flashcart (also don't ask me about these).

Do note that the ROM hack (and thus the patch) is > the original game size (2MB vs. 512KB).
Some IPS Patchers may have trouble applying patches > the original ROM size.
If it does, use a hex editor or similar utility to pad the original Sonic 1 rom to 2MB,
and apply the "base" and then the "extra" patches. Otherwise, Stealth Patch
(SPatch, at http://stealth.hapisan.com/Utils/StealthPatch/) is a known-working Windows-based patcher
(mirror of it at http://info.sonicretro.org/StealthPatch). Use Stealth Patch to patch with "base+extra" patch.

===============================

3. Features


■Modified menus

    ●New SEGA Chant, SSRG Logo screen
    ●New Title Screen with options to toggle extended music playlist and bonus stages
        ○Press B or C buttons on title screen, respectively
    ●Level Select cheat (Up-Down-Left-Right) enables both level select and Debug Mode cheats
    ●New Level Select screen, with 3 pages of levels

■New Zones, title cards, level and cycling palettes, art, level layouts, deformed backgrounds, etc.

    ●Title cards have been extended to handle acts 1-7 (especially for High Speed Zone)

    ●Normal levels
        ○Each zone has 3 acts
            ●2 are pure ports from Socket
            ●3rd act is original, has a boss room
        ○The Zones
            ●Emerald Forest Zone (EFZ)
            ●Treasure Castle Zone (TrCZ)
            ●Olein Cavern Zone (OCZ)
            ●Antiquity Zone (AZ)
            ●Stone Age Zone (SAZ, New)
            ●Future Zone (FZ)
            ●Time Castle Zone (TCZ)
            ●Time Lord Zone (TLZ, formerly Final Zone)

    ●Bonus levels
        ○Each level has either 2 or 3 acts
            ●Levels can be accessed by jumping onto a door object in a level
            ●Completing the level/dying takes you back to previous level. No lives are decremented
            ●Completing the level warps you elsewhere in the previous level
        ○The Zones
            ●Lights (BZL)
            ●Castle (BZC)
            ●Lava (BZLa)
            ●Fence (BZF)

    ●Special Stages
        ○Normal S1 rotating special stages have been replaced with standard platforming levels.
            ●Reaching the signpost without dying will award you a Chaos emerald via the Special Stage Results screen
            ●Dying will not award you a Chaos emerald, but will not decrement lives.
            ●Obtaining 50 rings in the zone will earn you a continue (disabled in the v0.3 demo)
        ○Each special stage are ports of the "High Speed Zone" acts from Socket

■New YM2612 tunes

    ●MegaPCM Driver
    ●Ports of Socket music
    ●New music for the other acts of levels in the extended playlist,
    a separate "good"/"bad" playlist (based if Sonic has all the chaos emeralds) for some levels

    ●Music slots ranging from $80-$9F and expanded to $E5 - $FF

■New/ported objects where necessary

    ●New object art/mappings where necessary
    ●Custom door object for level warps
    ●Art edits

■Various SCHG/SSRG bug fixes and tutorials, and other original code

    ●Expanded Sonic 1 Water tables (AZ and BZLa)
    ●Implemented Sonic 1 ROM Chunks and removal of Sonic 1 loop system (ROM chunks now expanded upto $FF chunks, new)
    ●Touch-pop monitors
    ●S1 New zone guide
    ●Walk-jump, spike, and other bug fixes
    ●Zone-agnostic objects
    ●Spindash
    ●Boss areas
    ●Title Card has its own song
===============================

4. Credits

    ■Tutorials
        ●MarkeyJester: Old SSRG Logo
        ●Mercury: Zone Agnostic objects
        ●FraGag: Sonic 1 ROM Chunks guide
        ●VladikComper: MegaPCM, PCM2DPCM Converter
        ●Tornado: Sonic 1 Water Guide (for AZ, BZLa)
        ●Other people
    ■Help
        ●ProjectFM, Clownacy, Nineko, MainMemory: Help with expanding ROM Chunks to $FF/Basic Q&A
        ●LuigiXHero: Hack help
        ●Firerat: Optimizations on the game's object handler and other bugfixes
        ●Nineko: Rainbow Road song (from his publicly released SoniNeko SMPS pack, for Bonus Zone Fence FG2)
        ●AbysmalLeopard: Enlarged GHZ Ball and Level Select BG art
        ●"Jakob": IRL friend bug testing on real hardware

    ■Tools
        ●Editors/Misc
            ○Techokami: Socketripper phps script and level rips at spriters-resource
            (this hack wouldn't exist without it!)
            
	    ○MainMemory: SonLVL and S2NA support
        ●Art
            ○Clownancy (et. al.): Capt. PlanED
            ○KanedaFR: Gens KMod (for ripping art and palettes)
            ○Selbi: Sonic 1 Text Editor, Selbi's Parallax Editor
            ○ComputerNerd/Sonic16 (IIRC): RetroGraphicsToolkit
            ○Hivebrain: PCXPal v4.0
            ○Xenowhirl: SonMapED
        ●Audio
            ○Puto, Nineko: XM3SMPS and XM4SMPS
            ○ValleyBell: VGM2MID, MID2SMPS, SMPSPlay, PCM2DPCM Converter, GRC2MID
            ○Apollolux: VGM2PRE
            ○Shiru: VGM Music Maker

===============================

5. Known Bugs

●Completing the final zone for demo (Antiquity Zone 3) sends player back to the Sega screen

●Inability to obtain all 6 emeralds in normal gameplay.
Big Ring object disabled when trying to access HSZ6,
due to issues in the modified SS layout loader loading HSZ6.

●Special Stage Results screen does not actually award a Continue upon collecting 50+ rings,
disabled due to issues with the Continue Screen

●Bosses are disabled, and boss areas are incomplete.
The end-level capsule is there, though, for completing the level

●Screen tearing issues when using warp doors and in BZF

===============================

6. Change Log:

■v0.3 (SHC16 build)

    ●Created readme in zip file
    ●Available zones in demo
        ○EFZ
        ○TrCZ
        ○OCZ
        ○SAZ
        ○AZ
        ○HSZ1-5
        ○BZF, BZC, BZLa, BZL

    ●Menu changes
        ○Added "Press Start to Skip/Continue" text on SEGA screen
        ○Created new Title Screen and ROM info, better graphics for Level Select

    ●Bug Fixes
        ○Fixed warp issues with returning back to a standard platform level after special stages
        ○Improved collision slightly for elbow and S-ramps, quarter pipes (still not perfect)
        ○Fixed issue with dying at top of level
        ○Fixed issue with falling through chunk solidarity if falling too fast
        ○Fixed issue with extended playlist not playing if on and after using invincibility
        ○Added loop to invincibility song
        ○Added highlight to solid blocks and fixed palette issues in BZL

        ○Object/objpos changes
            ●Imported better graphics for
                ○Collasping plat/breakable wall in TrCZ
                ○Small SBZ door in TrCZ, SAZ
                ○Ball pedestal in OCZ
                ○Chopper in EFZ, AZ

            ●Enabled priority for all moving spikes
            ●Added rings to beginning of all levels
            ●Re-enabled and fixed animals in HSZ, BZF, and SAZ
            ●Improved collision with touch-pop monitors

            ●Title Cards
                ○Created better art for "V" letter in the title card mappings
                ○Added text to indicate FG or BG layer in BZF
                ○Gave Title Card its own song upon appearance in non-bonus, non-special stages, and when not warping

            ●Various minor objpos changes in levels

        ○Other bugs/user-reported issues I can't remember

■v0.2 08/xx/16
■v0.1 03/xx/16
===============================


EOF